"Ginkgo and Nicotinamide for Glaucoma Treatment"
Glaucoma is now
the leading cause
of irreversible vision loss
in the world.
It's caused by the deterioration
of the optic nerve
that connects the eye
to the brain.
Most commonly this is due
to excessive pressure
inside the eyeball.
Ginkgo biloba is one
of the most common supplements
taken by glaucoma sufferers.
It doesn't seem to lower
intraocular pressure,
but MRI studies suggest
ginkgo supplements may increase
cerebral blood flow
in the brain.
What about blood flow
to the eyes?
Ginkgo increases
ocular blood flow
in both normal
and glaucomatous subjects;
so, it was put to the test.
Compared to sugar pills,
40 milligrams
of a ginkgo extract twice a day,
on top of their regular
anti-glaucoma medications,
appeared to significantly slow
the progression
of visual defects
in open-angle glaucoma patients,
the most common type,
though it's not clear
in this study
if the participants
were properly randomized.
Aside from
a single published case report
of visual improvements
after ginkgo supplementation,
there don't appear
to be any other studies
on open-angle glaucoma,
but there have been
two interventional trials
on the less common
normal tension type.
They were both randomized,
double-blind,
placebo-controlled
crossover trials
using the same dose
and duration.
One found
a significant benefit,
an improvement in pre-existing
visual field damage,
but the other found
no benefit at all.
If you want to try it despite
the underwhelming results,
make sure to first discuss with
your healthcare professional
due to a possible increase
in bleeding risk from the herb.
Any other supplement
possibilities?
In 2017,
extraordinary results
were reported
in a leading scientific journal.
Nicotinamide,
a form of vitamin B3,
was able to prevent
the development of glaucoma
in aged mice
prone to the disease,
with more than 90 percent
effectiveness.
Moderate or severe nerve damage
was found in about two-thirds
of the control mice,
but 93 percent of the mice
given nicotinamide had none.
The researchers concluded,
"The degree of protection
afforded by administering
this single molecule
is unprecedented
and unanticipated."
A commentary on the study
published in the New England
Journal of Medicine entitled,
"Nicking Glaucoma
with Nicotinamide?"
suggested clinical trials
should be initiated.
The researchers thought
to give it a try
based on the fact
that glaucomatous mice
had a comparable deficiency
in NAD+,
from which nicotinamide
is a precursor.
Is that even the case in people?
Apparently so.
Those with glaucoma
have about a third lower
nicotinamide levels
in their blood
compared to age-matched peers.
And greater intake of niacin,
which is another form of B3,
is associated
with less glaucoma.
It was time
to put it to the test,
and the title gives it away.
In 2020,
an international team
of researchers
published a study
in which glaucoma patients
were randomized
to nicotinamide or placebo
for 12 weeks and then switched
for another 12 weeks.
And significantly fewer patients
suffered further
visual field deterioration
while on the nicotinamide,
4 percent versus 12 percent
while on placebo.
A 2022 study found significant
improvements in visual function
compared to placebo
within two months,
but it's not
directly comparable,
since they also added pyruvate,
which is another component
of energy metabolism.
For a discussion of cost,
labeling confusion,
and potential side effects
of taking nicotinamide,
check out the NAD chapter
in my book How Not to Age,
in which I go through
the pros and cons
of all nine
NAD-boosting supplements,
it's like a tongue twister:
NA, NAM, NMN, NR,
NAD, NADH, NMNH, NRH,
tryptophan.
Or you just stay tuned here
on NutritionFacts.org
for an upcoming series
of videos on the subject.